Guide to Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen, District 356 (Black Eagle, Mont.) records. 1896-1967
Montana Historical Society Research Center
Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen, District 356 (Black Eagle, Mont.) records,
1896-1967
Montana Historical Society, Research Center Archives Archives 225 N. Roberts PO Box 201201 Helena MT 59620-1201 (406) 444-2681 MHSlibrary@mt.gov
MC 345
Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen, District 356 (Black Eagle, Mont.)
5.5 linear feet of shelf space
The Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen had a local division in Great Falls and Black Eagle, Montana. Records include interoffice correspondence, general correspondence, financial records, minutes and other organizational records, subject files, and miscellany.
Historical Note
The Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen was formed as the Conductors' Brotherhood, in 1868. The first convention was held that fall in spite of a threat by the Chicago, Burlington and Quincy Railroad to fire any conductor who joined. The 1878 convention formally changed the name to the Order of Railway Conductors of America. The national headquarters were established in Cedar Rapids, Iowa. During its early years the order was primarily a fraternal and benevolent association. Beginning in 1885 the Order began negotiating with the railroads concerning wages and working conditions. It also began lobbying Congress to pass hours legislation.
In 1954 the Order changed its name to the Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen, in recognition of the long-standing practice of accepting Brakemen into the order. In 1969, the Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen merged with three other Brotherhoods to form the United Transportation Union.
The Black Eagle local of ORC was founded in 1894 and remained active through 1963.
Records of the Order of Railway Conductors and its successor the Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen consist primarily of interoffice correspondence and minutes. The interoffice correspondence is divided into correspondence (1915-1955) of the local with its members and with other locals; correspondence (1919-1945) of the Legislative Board, grievance correspondence (1914-1922), correspondence (1918-1961) with the ORC's General Chairman for the Great Northern Railway, located in St. Paul, Minnesota; and circular letters (1915-1959) from the national Order in Cedar Rapids, Iowa. There is general correspondence (1913-1960) with the Great Northern Railway and with others.
There are minute books for Division #356 from its founding in 1896 through 1938. In addition, there are minutes of the Railroad Brotherhoods Legislative Board, and of several committees of which ORC was a part. Other organizational records consist of members petitions for membership arranged alphabetically, members' dues ledgers (1896-1940), national lists of dismissed and reinstated members, and seniority lists.
There are annual (1920-1951) and quarterly (1918-1922) reports of the ORC's General Chairman for the Great Northern Railway, reports (1905-1949) of the Railroad Brotherhoods Joint Legislative Board, subject files on a variety of political and government organizations, and miscellany.
Arranged by series
Collection is open for research
Acquisition information available upon request.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Labor unions--Montana.
Railroad brakemen--Montana.
Railroad conductors--Montana.
Black Eagle (Mont.)
Great Falls (Mont.)
Montana
Labor Unions
Railroads
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Interoffice Correspondence
  - Chronological (with members and with other divisions), 1915-1955 (Box-folder 1 / 1-4)
  - Legislative Board, 1919-1945 (Box-folder 1 / 5-7)
  - Correspondence re grievances of members: A-W, 1910-1922 (Box-folder 1 / 8-13)
  - ORC General Chairman for Great Northern Railway (includes T. F. Richardson, P. C. Bradley, J. A. Gannon, R. E. Landis), 1918-1935 (Box-folder 1 / 14-15)
  - ORC General Chairman for Great Northern Railway (includes R. E. Landis, H. N. Hansen, Myles J. Milner, L. E. Downing, R. K. Foster), 1936-1961 (Box-folder 2 / 1-10)
  - ORC National Offices, 1915-1951 (Box-folder 2 / 11)
  - ORC National Offices: circular letters, 1915-1958 (Box-folder 3 / 1-8)
- General Correspondence
  - Great Northern Railway, 1913-1946, 1960 (Box-folder 3 / 9-10)
  - Chronological (includes other railroad brotherhoods, Congressmen, political committees, etc.), 1918-1957 (Box-folder 3 / 11-15)
- Financial Records
  - Accident insurance dept. reports (national), 1937-1950 (Box-folder 4 / 1)
  - Accident insurance materials, undated (Box-folder 4 / 2)
  - Cash books, 1940-1960 (Box-folder 4 / 3-4)
  - Checkstubs, 1959-1961 (Box-folder 4 / 5)
  - Division Trustees financial reports, 1924-1925, 1933-1941, 1958 (Box-folder 4 / 6)
  - Members ledgers (includes some personal data and treasurers' journal), 1896-1911 (Box-folder 4 / 7-8)
  - Members ledgers (includes some personal data and treasurers' journal), 1910-1933 (Box-folder 5 / 1-3)
  - Members ledgers (includes some personal data and treasurers' journal), 1932-1940 (Box-folder 6 / 1-2)
  - ORC Montana Legislative Board financial reports, 1924-1934 (Box-folder 6 / 3)
  - ORC Mutual Benefit Dept. premium rates and certificate values, 1945 (Box-folder 6 / 4)
  - ORC National Trustees circulars (financial reports), 1937-1946 (Box-folder 6 / 5)
- Legal Documents
  - Agreements and contracts, 1917-1936 (Box-folder 6 / 6)
  - Dockets (includes National Railroad Board of Adjustment; Montana Board of Railroad Commissioners), 1932-1957 (Box-folder 6 / 7)
  - Great Northern Railway Company schedule for conductors (contracts with ORC), 1917-1957 (Box-folder 6 / 8)
  - Great Northern Railway Company schedule for trainmen and yardmen (contracts with ORC), 1912-1924 (Box-folder 6 / 9)
- Minutes
  - Minute books (Division #356), 1896-1916 (Box-folder 7 / 1-4)
  - Minutes (Division #356), 1914-1938, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 8 / 1-5)
  - Minutes (General Committee for Great Northern Railway), 1918-1941, 1953 (Box-folder 8 / 6-11)
  - Minutes (ORC Association for Districts 1, 2 and 3), 1931-1932 (Box-folder 8 / 12)
  - Minutes (ORC Legislative Board: scattered), 1915-1940 (Box-folder 8 / 13)
  - Minutes (ORC statewide), 1922 (Box-folder 8 / 14)
  - Minutes (Yardmasters' Committee), 1949 (Box-folder 8 / 15)
  - Minutes (grievance conference), 1956 (Box-folder 8 / 16)
- Organizational Records
  - Bylaws (Division #356), 1898 (Box-folder 8 / 17)
  - Directories (National), 1956, 1967 (Box-folder 8 / 18)
  - "Form of questions to be answered by candidate" (members' oath), undated (Box-folder 8 / 19)
  - Membership petitions: A-Z (applications for membership), 1930s-1950s (Box-folder 9 / 1-2)
  - National constitutions [scattered], 1909-1962 (Box-folder 9 / 3-4)
  - National withdrawals and reinstatements (includes Montana members), 1937-1946 (Box-folder 9 / 5)
  - Resolutions, 1918-1933, undated (Box-folder 9 / 6)
  - Ritual manual, 1911, 1958 (Box-folder 9 / 7)
  - Seniority lists, 1956-1959 (Box-folder 9 / 8)
- Reports
  - Annual reports of General Chairman for Great Northern Railway (includes J. A. Gannon, W. E. Johnson, R. E. Landis, H. N. Hansen, Myles J. Milner), 1920-1951 (Box-folder 10 / 1-15)
  - Quarterly reports of General Chairman for Great Northern Railway (includes T. F. Richardson, J. A. Gannon), 1920-1951 (Box-folder 11 / 1-2)
  - "Fifteen years under the Railway Labor Act, amended and the National Mediation Board", 1950 (Box-folder 11 / 3)
  - "Handbook for reporting under the railroad retirement and unemployment insurance laws", 1964, 1967 (Box-folder 11 / 4)
  - Mutual Benefit Dept. report, 1944 (Box-folder 11 / 5)
  - National Mediation Board report, 1967 (Box-folder 11 / 6)
  - Railroad Brotherhoods Joint Legislative Board report [scattered], 1905-1949 (Box-folder 11 / 7)
  - Report of committee on busses in competition with railroads, ca. 1936 (Box-folder 11 / 8)
  - Reports of conferences between Order of Railway Conductors, Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen et al., 1921-1922 (Box-folder 11 / 9)
  - Report of Black Eagle delegate E. L. Sjaholm to 43rd Session Grand Division, 1946 (Box-folder 11 / 10)
  - Report on national legislation, 1920 (Box-folder 11 / 11)
  - Report on proceedings in connection with 1919-1920 wage movement (Box-folder 11 / 12)
  - "The Wages of railroad labor", 1938 (Box-folder 11 / 13)
- Subject Files
  - Conference for Progressive Political Action, 1922-1924 (Box-folder 11 / 14)
  - Legislation (includes Railroad Brotherhoods report on Montana legislature, Congressional Records, several bills), 1928-1941 (Box-folder 11 / 15)
  - Manpower problem during World War II, 1943 (Box-folder 11 / 16)
  - National Youth Administration, Montana, 1935 (Box-folder 11 / 17)
  - Office of Price Administration Labor Office Information Service, 1943 (Box-folder 11 / 18)
  - President's Emergency Board, 1928, 1955 (Box-folder 11 / 19)
  - Railroad Amalgamated Conference for the Northwest District, 1923 (Box-folder 11 / 20)
  - Railway Board of Adjustment decisions, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 11 / 21)
  - Schedule revision proposal (re wages), 1920 (Box-folder 11 / 22)
  - U. S. Railroad Administration, 1918 (Box-folder 11 / 23)
  - U. S. Railroad Labor Board, 1920-1921 (Box-folder 11 / 24)
  - World War II bond drives, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 11 / 25)
- Miscellany
  - Certificates (includes Co-operative Broom Manufacturing Company stock certificate, Plumb Plan League membership certificate, Official Commendation re payroll savings plan), 1905, 1919, ca.1944 (Box-folder 11 / 26)
  - Meeting announcement poster, undated (Box-folder 11 / 27)
  - Propositions by railroad brotherhoods, 1920 (Box-folder 11 / 28)
  - Railroad Retirement Tax Act, 1965-1967 (Box-folder 11 / 29)
  - "Rules and regulations governing admission to Order of Railway Conductors Home" (application of J. H. Stricklan), 1930 (Box-folder 11 / 30)
  - Strike conduct instructions, 1950s (Box-folder 11 / 31)
  - Strikebreaker list: Missouri and Arkansas Railroad strike, 1921-1922? (Box-folder 11 / 32)
  - Transfer sheet: list of artifacts transferred to Museum program, undated (Box-folder 11 / 33)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box-folder 11 / 34)